

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Hobart, Tasmania, Australia

८+61 466 683 552 | **≥**toddellis.wa@gmail.com

o toddellis | o tmichaelellis | ⊌ tootstorm | o 0000-0002-4410-8676 | o Todd-Ellis-4

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY_____

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

University of Tasmania

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia
2019 - present

- Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Bellingham, WA, USA

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

San Marcos, TX, USA

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - present

- Developing statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managing design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Designing and implementing programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff}$
- Overseeing development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - present

- · Developing complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- Overseeing multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- · Managing custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- Collaborating with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Sustainability Analyst

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2019-10 - 2021-02

2018-12 - 2019-05

- Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes
- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings
- Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

• Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets

- Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

Faculty Research Assistant

Wenatchee, WA, USA

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

2017-11 - 2018-06

- · Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

Biological Science Technician II

Ridgefield, WA, USA

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- · Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment

2017-08 - 2017-11

CONSULTING _____

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity

USD\$2,500

U.S. Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate

USD\$2,500

HONOURS

2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research

AUD\$10,000

2021-09 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-08 Certifi-Cat of Appreciation

Australian Museum

Ten Lives Cat Centre

2020-08 Bushfire Data Quest 2020

Frontier Development Lab

2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)

AUD\$5,000 p.a.

2017-01 - 2017-11

2018-06 **Best Fish and Wildlife Science**

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2017-10 Conservation Award

PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE ____

Foster Parent Hobart, TAS, Australia

TEN LIVES CAT CENTRE 2020-05 - present

Animal Handler

New Braunfels, TX, USA

Humane Society of the New Braunfels Area 2018-08 - 2019-01

Animal Handler Wenatchee, WA, USA

Wenatchee Valley Humane Society 2018-03 - 2018-08

Technology TutorNORTH CENTRAL REGIONAL LIBRARY

2018-01 - 2018-08

2018-01 - 2018-08

Geographic Information Systems Technician Portland, OR, USA

Assistant Librarian Kelso, WA, USA

BEACON HILL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL 2017-01 - 2017-11